Finding Aid for Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States, Michigan Commandery Records, 1885-1951
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States, Michigan Commandery Records 1885-1951, 1885-1931
Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States. Michigan Commandery.
6 microfilms 3 linear feet, 1 oversize manuscript volume, and 6 published volumes
98111 mf 292c-mf 297c
Membership applications containing biographical data and summary of military record; index to membership applications; membership register; minutes, 1901-1927; financial records, 1885-1931; library records; and twenty-six reminiscences and papers of Union veterans.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the Commandery (donor 2205 ) in 1946 with an additional deposit in 1955.
The record group is open to research.
Subjects:
Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States. Michigan Commandery.; Soldiers--Michigan.; United States. Army. Illinois Infantry Regiment, 52nd (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 10th (1863-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 1st (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1861-1864). Company E.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 5th (1861-1865). Company B.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1865). Company A.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1865). Company D.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 14th (1862-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 16th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 18th (1862-1865). Company C.; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 26th (1861-1863). Company C.; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 160th (1862-1865); Veterans--Michigan--Societies, etc.; United States. Army. Illinois Cavalry Regiment, 7th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Colored Infantry Regiment, 114th (1864-1867); United States. Army. Michigan Artillery Regiment, 1st (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1861-1864); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 17th (1862-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 19th (1862-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Sharpshooters Regiment, 1st (1863-1865); United States. Army. Minnesota Infantry Regiment, 11th (1864-1865). Company C.; United States. Army. Missouri Infantry Regiment (U.S. Reserve Corps), 2nd (1861); United States. Army. Missouri Infantry Regiment (U.S. Reserve Corps), 2nd (1861-1862); United States. Army. Missouri Infantry Regiment, 25th (1861-1864); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Chaplains.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Poetry.; Applington, Zenos, d. 1862.; Atlanta Campaign, 1864.; Cuba.; Fredericksburg (Va.), Battle of, 1862.; Gettysburg (Pa.), Battle of, 1863.; Jonesboro (Ga.), Battle of, 1864.; Munfordville (Ky.), Battle of, 1862.; Stones River, Battle of, Murfreesboro, Tenn., 1862-1863.; Shiloh, Battle of, Tenn., 1862.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Personal narratives, American.; Stoneman's Raid, 1865.; Swift, Frederick W., 1831-; Kedzie, Robert Clark, 1823-1902.
Contributors:
Arndt, Albert F. R.; Atkinson, William F.; Baldwin, Frank Dwight.; Bump, Orrin.; Campbell, Robert H.; Carrington, Edward.; Case, Leverette N.; Claxton, William C.; Drake, Ludlum C.; Farrar, Judson S.; Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921.; Hampton, C. G.; Hopper, George C.; Jacklin, Rufus W.; Kallman, Herman.; Mizner, Henry R.; Pealer, Russell R.; Poe, O. M. (Orlando Metcalfe), 1832-1895.; Potter, Theodore Edgar, 1832-1910.; Putnam, William.; Seage, Henry Stark, d. 1899.; Shurly, E. R. P.; Trowbridge, L. S. (Luther Stephen), 1836-1912.; Vander Veen, Arand.; Waters, D. R.; Wolcott, Laurens W.
- War reminiscences
  - Arndt, Albert F.R. (Major, 1st Michigan Artillery), "Facts and reminiscences of the War of the Rebellion of 1861-65," 1908 (Reel 1)
  - Atkinson, William F., "F.W. Swift," 1904 (Poem about Frederick W. Swift, Major, 17th Michigan Infantry) (Reel 1)
  - Baldwin, F.D. (Captain, 19th Michigan Infantry, later U.S. Army officer). "Memorandum of services, Colonel Frank D. Baldwin 1861 to 1900," ca. 1901 (Reel 1)
  - Bump, Orrin (Lieutenant, Co. A, 8th Michigan Infantry), "Expedition to South Carolina in 1861-2," undated (Reel 1)
  - Campbell, Robert H. (First Lieutenant and Quartermaster), "Service with the old 4th Mich. Infantry," undated (Reel 1)
  - Carrington, Edward, "A reminiscence of the Civil War," 1901 (Reel 1)
    (Poem headed "Head Quarters First Army Corps, Army of the Potomac, on the Rapidan, February 6, 1864," with later introduction)
  - Case, Leverette N. (Captain, 1st Michigan Sharpshooters), "At Petersburg!," 1902 (Reel 1)
  - Claxton, William C. (Second Lieutenant, 1st Missouri Engineers), "Thirty-nine years after the Battle of Shiloh," 1901 (Reel 1)
  - Drake, Ludlum C. (Corporal, Co. C, 18th Michigan Infantry, later Lieutenant, 114th U.S. Colored Infantry), "Recollections of the Civil War," undated (Reel 1)
  - Farrar, Judson S. (Captain, Co. B), "From Williamsburg to Harrison's Landing, with the Fifth Mich. Infty. 1862," undated (Reel 1)
  - Grant, Claudius B., "Remarks made by Judge C.B. Grant at funeral of Dr. Robert C. Kedzie," 1902 (Reel 1)
    (Kedzie was surgeon in 12th Michigan Infantry; paper includes no mention of Civil War)
  - Hampton, C.G., untitled paper describing description of activities in Cuba after Spanish American War 1899 (Reel 1)
  - Hopper, George G. (Major), "From Beverley Fork to Bottoms Bridge with the 1st Michigan Infantry from May 1st to June 6th [1864]," 1913 (Reel 1)
  - Jacklin, Rufus W. (Major, 16th Michigan Infantry), "Gettysburg," 1903 (Reel 1)
  - Kallman, H. (Colonel, 2nd Missouri U.S. Reserve Corps Infantry), "Col. Kallman's story" and Reminiscences," undated (Reel 1)
    (2 different reminiscences)
  - Mizner, Henry R. (Colonel), "The Fourteenth Michigan Infantry, the Battle of Murfreesboro, Tennessee, the Battle of Jonesboro, Georgia, and incidents of army life," undated (Reel 1)
  - Pealer, Russell R., "Address at the annual banquet at the Charlevoix," 1907 (Reel 1)
    (remarks about the MOLLUS organization, by the Dept. Commander)
  - Poe, Orlando M., "Gen. Poe's introduction of Gen. P. St. George Cooke at the banquet of April 1885" (Reel 1)
    (remarks introducing the toast "The Old Flag")
  - Potter, Theodore E. (Captain, Co. C, 11th Minnesota Infantry), "Military reminiscences of Theodore E. Potter," 1900 (Reel 1)
  - Putnam, William (Chaplain, 160th New York Infantry), "Army chaplains' work in time of war," 1901 (Reel 1)
  - Seage, Henry S. (Color Sergeant, Co. E, 4th Michigan Infantry), "Battle of Fredericksburg," 1899 (Reel 1)
  - Shurly, E.R.P. (Captain, Co. C, 26th New York Infantry), "Reminiscence of the War of the Rebellion, 1861," 1904 (Reel 1)
  - Trowbridge, L.S. (Colonel, 10th Michigan Cavalry), "A continuation of the narrative of the Stoneman Raid of 1865 terminating in the pursuit of Jefferson Davis," 1902 and "The surrender of Munfordsville," 1906 (Reel 1)
  - Vanderveen, Arend (Assistant Surgeon, Co. D, 8th Michigan Infantry), untitled reminiscence 1915 (Reel 1)
  - Waters, D.R., "The brave death of Major Zenos Applington, May 15, 1862," undated (Reel 1)
    (Applington commanded a battalion of the 7th Illinois Cavalry)
  - Wolcott, Laurens W. (First Lieutenant, 52nd Illinois Infantry), "A sketch of the Battle of Atlanta, with some personal reminiscences," 1903 (Reel 1)
- Organizational materials
  - Clippings, notes, banquet invitations (Reel 1)
  - Applications for membership
    - Index, no. 1-450 (Reel 1)
    - No. 1-147 1885-1887 (Reel 1)
    - No. 148-294 1887-1892 (Reel 2)
    - No. 295-450 1892-1902 (Reel 2)
    - No. 451-599 1902-1915 (Reel 3)
    - No. 600-704 1915-1951 (Reel 3)
  - Ledger 1918-1931 (Reel 4)
  - Minutes 1901-1927 (Reel 4)
  - Minutes (draft) 1909-1929 (Reel 4)
  - Account book 1894-1931 (Reel 4)
  - Cash book
    - 1885-1930 (Reel 4)
    - 1931 (Reel 5)
  - Catalogue of books, library of the Michigan Commandery Loyal Legion of U.S. 1906 (Reel 5)
  - Catalogue of maps & books, Michigan Commandery Loyal Legion 1914 (Reel 5)
  - Receipt book 1885-1931 (Reel 5)
  - Visitors' register 1891-1932 (Reel 5)
- Published volumes
  - War papers read before the Commandery of the State of Michigan Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States
    - Vol. 1: October 6, 1886-April 6, 1893 (Reel 5)
    - Vol. 2: December 7, 1893-May 5, 1898 (Reel 5)
  - Circulars
    - 1885-1897 (Reel 5)
    - 1891-1894 (Reel 6)
    - 1898-1910 (Reel 6)
    - 1911-1919 (Reel 6)